Okay, בקר טוב, Boker Tov, today's דף Daf is
ק"י Kuf Yud but we start with ק"ט עמוד ב', Kuf Tes
amud beis, we pick up where we'll read the משנה Mishna again
quickly. אין אוכלין אזובון בשבת לפי שאינו מאכל בריאים. Ein ochlin ezovon
b'shabbos l'fi she'eino ma'achal b'ri'im. You can't eat אזובון ezovon on שבת
Shabbos because it's not what healthy people eat and again it's a
type of a רפואה refuah and it's obvious that the only person
who would eat this is somebody who's eating it for health purposes.
אבל אוכל הוא את יועזר, Aval ochel hu es Yo'ezer,
you can eat יועזר Yo'ezer whatever that is, which maybe sometimes would
be eaten for health purposes but sometimes for other legitimate purposes, non-health
purposes as well. ושותה אבוברוא, V'shoseh abuvroa, you could also drink that
because of same issues, that it would be enough eaten by under
normal circumstances. כל האוכלים אוכל אדם לרפואה וכל המשקין שותה חוץ ממי
דקלים, Kol ha'ochalim ochel adam l'refuah v'chol hamashkin shoseh chutz mi'mei dekalim,
as you can eat all types of food even if you're doing
it for health purposes or for normal foods, foods that people eat
in general, and similar all types of drink with the exception of
water of palm trees, we'll see what that is, וכוס עיקרין v'chos
ikarin and a cup of some type of a liquid that was
soaked in roots, roots of various plants, that those are clearly done
for medicinal purposes. מפני שהן לירוקא Mipnei shehen l'yeroka because those are
done for jaundice. אבל שותה הוא מי דקלים לצמאו, Aval shoseh hu
mi dekalim l'tzma'o, but you can drink this these water from palm
trees if you're thirsty, וסך שמן עיקרין שלא לרפואה v'sach shemen ikarin
shelo l'refuah and you can use this oil in roots if it's
not done for רפואה, refuah, so you need the combination of two
things. You need that it be the type of a thing that
your intention is not enough of a problem. If it's the type
of a thing that is not, you know, clearly being done for
the purposes of רפואה refuah and even if it's the type of
thing that is normally done for the purposes of רפואה, refuah, that's
the assumptions people will have, if that's not your motivation that's not
a problem either. You need the combination of your motivation and that
it is the type of thing that is standardly done for רפואה.
refuah. גמרא, Gemara, okay, and we're not concerned with מראית עין. Maris
Ayin. אמר רב יוסף, Amar Rav Yosef, איזו, Eizo, what's איזו ezov
at mentioned in the תורה Torah when it speaks about dipping, you
know, אגודת אזוב agudas ezov in various things for the blood for
פסח Pesach or for the טהרה tahara of the מצורע? metzora? אברתא
בר חמא, Abarta bar Chama, it's this thing called a אברתא בר
חמא. Abarta bar Chama. אברתא בר חמא Abarta bar Chama is the
specific, you know, sort of strand of this אברתא, Abarta, which presumably
we translate this as hyssop. אזובון, Ezovon, the אזובון ezovyon or whatever
mentioned in the משנה Mishna is אברתא בר הינג, Abarta bar Hinag,
okay, a different strand of that same plant. עולא אמר Ulla amar
מרוא חיורא. Maru chivra. עולא Ulla says no, actually the אזוב ezov
in the תורה Torah is this thing called מרוא חיורא, Maru chivra,
white מרוא. maru.
You usually hear sage.
Okay, fine, white sage.
עולא איקלע לבי רב שמואל בר יהודה, Ulla itkla l'bei Rav Shmuel
bar Yehuda, אייתו לקמיה מרוא חיורא, ayisu l'kamei Maru chivra, so עולא
Ulla came to the house of רב שמואל בר יהודה, Rav Shmuel
bar Yehuda, they brought in front of him this white
מרוא. maru. אמר היינו אזוב דכתיבא באורייתא, Amar heinu Ezov d'kesiva b'Oraisa,
so he was הלכה halacha man, he only looked at everything through
the lens of the תורה, Torah, so they brought him something, they
said oh, this is the אזוב ezov that's written in the תורה.
Torah. Okay. רב פפא אמר Rav Pappa amar שומשוק, Shumshuk, that the
אזוב ezov of the תורה Torah is
שומשוק. shumshuk. אמר רב ירמיה מדיפתי, Amar Rav Yirmeya miDifti, כוותיה דרב
פפא מסתברא, K'vasei d'Rav Pappa mistabra, it makes sense. דתנן, D'tnan, מצות
אזוב שלשה קלחים, Mitzvas Ezov shlosha klachim, the way you do the
אזוב ezov like again by dipping it in the, you know, for
the פרה אדומה Para Aduma and for the splashes is you take
three, three separate like, you know, stalks, ובהן שלשה גבעולין, u'vahen shlosha
givolin, each stalk has like three, you know, stems coming out of
it. ושומשוק הוא דמשתכח הכי, V'shumshuk hu d'mishtakach hachi, and שומשוק shumshuk
is something you find this that has like three different like stems
coming out, coming out of the stalk. So it makes sense that
that's what אזוב. ezov. למה אכלי ליה L'mai achli lei now, why
did people, back to the משנה, Mishna, eat this אזובון, ezovyon, what
were they trying to solve with this? So here with this, לכוקאני,
L'kukani, for כוקאני. kukani. There you go. So רש"י Rashi says כוקאני
kukani is tapeworms, stomach worms, intestinal worms actually. במאי אכלי ליה, B'mai
achli lei, what would they eat it with? Presumably there's an assumption
that they had to eat it with something for it to be
effective. בשבע תמרי אוכמתא, B'sheva tamrei uchmasa, with seven black dates. ממאי
הויא, Mimai havya, and how did people get this intestinal worms? מקמחא
דשערי, M'kimcha d'sha'ari, from a type of a flour of barley flour,
דחליף עליה ארבעין יומין d'chalif alei arbayin yomin that had 40 days
passed over it and not been eaten and not been preserved. Maybe
the barley got, maybe the flour got the worms. Exactly, בסדר. Beseder.
Okay,
but it is interesting the precise thing, seven dates, 40 days, you
know, you do wonder also how much there was these also, you
know, they thought other factors were at work here. Exactly. Exactly, yeah,
who knows. Okay. אבל אוכל הוא את יועזר, Aval ochel hu es
Yo'ezer, they can eat this יועזר, Yo'ezer, that was not so much
exclusively for health purposes. So מאי יועזר, Mai Yo'ezer, what is this?
פוטנא, Putna, so it's פוטנא. Putna. Wonderful, what do they say פוטנא
Putna is? It doesn't translate. All right, there you go, פוטנא, Putna,
so we're in the same boat. Okay, למה אכלי ליה, L'mai achli
lei, what would they eat it for? לאורקצא, L'urktza, for the problem
of אורקצא, urktza, which רש"י Rashi says is liver worms, worms in
the liver.
במאי אכלי ליה, B'mai achli lei, what would they eat with it...
What you eat with it to make it effective? בשבע תמרי חיורתא
Be-shava tamrei chivarta with seven white dates. ממאי הויא? Mi-mai havya? How
did people get this?
ממאי הויא? Mi-mai havya? Where am I?
מאומצא Mi-umtza from eating raw meat ומיא u-maya and
water אליבא ריקנא aliba rekana on an empty heart, meaning on an
empty stomach. I'm actually not, raw meat, it's not raw meat, it's
sort of like meat on charred on coals. And water on an
empty stomach. ומבשרא שמנא U-mibisra shamna from fatty meat אליבא ריקנא aliba
rekana on an empty stomach. ומבשרא דתורא U-mibisra de-tora and ox meat
אליבא ריקנא aliba rekana on an empty stomach. And then all of
these or any of these. מאגוזא Me-angoza and eating nuts אליבא ריקנא
aliba rekana on an empty stomach. ומגירי דרוביא U-migiri de-ruvya אליבא ריקנא
aliba rekana and from a,
and what is this? Oh yes, רש״י Rashi says, like some type
of leaves of a fenugreek, I think. All right, whatever. On an
empty heart. ומשתי מיא בתריה U-mishit maya batrey if you ate any
or all of these things and drank water afterwards. ואי לא Ve-ilo
and if this remedy was not
effective, לבלע תחלי חיורתא Liva-tachli chivarta you should swallow
white תחלי tachli which is what?
Cress, thank you. ואי לא Ve-ilo and if that didn't work, ליצום
דתעניתא Le-itzei de-tanisa then you should fast, ולייתי בשרא שמנא Ve-leiti bisra
shamna and then get fatty meat, which was one of the causes
of this, ולישדי אגומרי Ve-lishdi a-gumrei and throw it on coals, ולימץ
גרמא Ve-limatz garma and you should like, you should like suck out
a bone of this meat, ולגמע חלא Ve-ligma challa and swallow vinegar
and that'll help. ואיכא דאמרי Ve-ika de-amri some say חלא לא Challa
lo no don't do vinegar, משום דקשי לכבדא Mishum de-kashi le-kavda that'll
be hard for your liver. ואי לא Ve-ilo and if that doesn't
work, לייתי גורדא דאסינתא Leiti gurda de-asinta you should bring, what's this
again? Oh yes, you should bring like a scraped
bark דאסינתא de-asinta of from a
bush דגרידא מלעילא לתתא de-garida mi-le'eila le-tata that was scraped off of
it from top to bottom, ולא מתתא לעילא ve-lo mi-tata le-le'eila and
not scraped from the bottom to the
top, דילמא נפקא עדי פומיה dilma nafka adei pumei because if it,
you do the bark that was scraped the wrong way, the worm
will come up rather than go down, go out through your the
bottom, it'll come up through the top, it'll come out through your
mouth and that will not be and that'll be dangerous. Okay, ולישלקה
בשיכרא ve-lishlaka be-shichra and you should boil it in a beer, בי
שיבבי, bei shivvey, רש״י Rashi says two interpretations. Either it means בין
השמשות ben hashmashos like right at dusk, okay, or he means in
the house of a neighbor because if you do it maybe the
fumes from the boiling will be, will have a bad effect on
you, ולמחר u-le-machar and that sort of ties into the next point,
the next day, נסכרינהו לנקביה nisacharei le-nikvey you should seal up your
orifices, basically רש״י Rashi says like pinch your nose, דידיה, didei, ולישתי
ve-lishtei and drink it, so you got to drink it but don't
smell
it, ולישתי. ve-lishtei. וכי מפני Ve-ki mafnei and then when you relieve
yourself, מפני אפישכא דדיקלא mafnei a-pishcha de-dikla relieve yourself by the bark
of a palm tree and this will be the way to process
out this intestinal worm or this liver worm. Okay, so that's what
they would do that for.
I'm just wondering why this was preserved? This has nothing to do
with שבת Shabbos anymore, it's just folk medicine.
Right, but that's what for them it wasn't folk, it was medicine.
And then in the name of a rabbi, the whole thing.
Right, that's a good point. It's very much the סתמא stama of
the גמרא. Gemara.
So it kept getting copied as the scribes transferred. Right, right, and
it's stuck in the middle of הלכות halachos of שבת.
Shabbos. But I understand, I understand, but as I said before, I
think that, you know, okay, if you think that the idea is
is that it's like, you know, which I know is a concern
of you as like the rabbis know everything, okay, so then I
understand, but let's say you know, but like I keep on telling
you, I know this rabbi that got up once on ראש השנה
Rosh Hashanah and for his דרשה drasha said, "Everybody needs to check
the batteries in their smoke detectors." You know, so now you say,
"Well what, you're a rabbi, what's that your business?" You know, but
if you think that it's your business, the well-being of your congregants,
right? So if they were concerned about people's health and they believed
they actually had a tradition, you know, knowledge that this was helpful,
why shouldn't they transmit it?
Because then you're crossing over the line into a rabbi advising you
about...
is that different than the rabbi getting up and saying you should
check your smoke... but how do you know it's איסורא, asura, how
do you know it's not just somebody people listened to and therefore
he's concerned for their well-being and he's communicating what? Service announcement. It's
yeah, public service announcement. PSA.
Yeah, but it's so,
but nevertheless this is so outdated. For you! Right, well for you
too!
Right, I don't mean not for me, but I mean not for
the people who lived 2,000 years ago.
People revered this.
I understand, I actually think that even in ישיבות yeshivas where they
tend where they revere everything, I don't think they treat these medical
statements with the same in the same way. That's my general understanding,
yes.
Or do they? I'm reminded of the story about the rabbi in
Eastern Europe who during a cholera epidemic made קידוש Kiddush on יום
כיפור. Yom Kippur.
That's different, that's like a הלכתי halachic פסק, psak, you know.
But another example, I know a couple in Riverdale, she'd had
a
baby... husband's actually a doctor, but after looking at the medical stuff
about what the pros and cons were, they talked to a rabbi,
not about the medical stuff, but about how Judaism views taking personal
risks.
Okay, but all of those are cases where, it's not Rivka's point.
All of those are cases where there's a הלכה halakhic position.
That's right, exactly. But it's not, it's not... Right, so there are
times when one...
Right, but that's not what's going on here.
I agree. Okay, alright.
So now the גמרא...
Gemara... yeah. Well there were rabbis who were doctors too.
That's true.
Okay, שמואל Shmuel and... Right, exactly. Okay. ושוצין ארבו ברוע. v'shotzin arbu
b'roa. מאי ארבו
ברוע? mai arbu b'roa? חומטריא, chumtarya, okay, there you go. So מאי
חומטריא? mai chumtarya? חוטרא יחידא, chutra yechida, a single stalk. רש"י Rashi
says it's like a tree that grows... what does רש"י Rashi say?
אילנא דקאי יחידי, ilana d'kay yechidi, some type of a tree that
grows by itself and has no branches. All right, so this is
something... apparently. Apparently, yeah, exactly. למאי עבדי ליה? l'mai avdi lei? What
would you use this for? לגלויא, l'giluya, for water that had been
uncovered; they were afraid that uncovered water would be poisonous, would have
snake poison in it, so therefore this would be a remedy for
that. ואי לא, v'ei lo, and if this doesn't work, ליתי חמשא
כלילי, leisei chamsha klyly, take five roses, וחמשא כוסא דשיכרא, v'chamsha kusa
d'shichra, five cups of
beer, of mead, ונישלקינהו בהדי הדדי, v'nishlakinhu bahadi hadadi, and cook them
together, עד דקאי אאנפקא, ad d'kay a'anpaka, until it boils down to
an אנפקא, anpaka, which רש"י Rashi says is a רביעית, revi'is, like
a, you know, like a quarter of a לוג, log, like three
and a half ounces.
ונישתי, v'nishti, and drink it. אימיה דרב אחא בר אימי imei d'Rav
Acha bar Imi עבדא ליה לההוא גברא, avda lei l'hahu gavra, made
this for a certain man. חד כלילא וחד כוסא דשיכרא, chad klila
v'chad kusa d'shichra, the same proportions, one rose and one cup of
דשיכרא, d'shichra, שלקתיה, shalkatei, she boiled it, ואשקיתיה, v'ashkitei, and she had
him drink it. ושגרא תנורא, v'shagra tanura, and she lit the oven,
וגרפתיה, v'garfatei, and swept it out so it wouldn't be, you know,
boiling hot. ואותביתיה לבינתא בגוויה, v'oteivitei livinta b'gavei, and she put a
brick in the oven. Basically, so the oven had a lot of
retained heat; she put a brick down so he could sit not
directly on the floor of the oven which would have burnt him.
So basically putting him into like a hot room, okay, and therefore
with this drink and with this hot room, somehow he would sweat
it out or somehow that would that would get the poison out.
They believed that he had swallowed poison.
Okay. ונפק כהוצא ירקא, v'nafik k'hutza yarka, and a like a yellow
type of a, you know, thing came out of him, like a
yellow leaf, meaning basically the poison came out of him. He spit
up some type of some... not yellow, green, well, ירקא yarka can
be yellow-green. Anyway, he spit up some type of yellow-green phlegm and
that was the poison. רב אויא אמר, Rav Avya amar, רביעתא דחלבא
מעיזא חיורתא. reviata d'chalva m'iza chivarta. No, what you have to do
is you have to take
a רביעית revi'is of חלבא chalva from a white goat. רב הונא
בר יהודה אמר, Rav Huna bar Yehuda amar, ליתי אתרוגא חליא, leisei
etroga chalya, you should take a sweet אתרוג, etrog, ולחקיה, v'lichakei, and
make a hole in it, ולמליה דובשא, v'limlei duvsha, and fill the
hole with honey, ולאותביה ביני מילילי דנורא, v'leoteivya beini milulei d'nura, and
you should put it between the... what is it, the something of
the fire? רש"י Rashi says
right... רש"י Rashi says אמבייא ambaya like... אמבייא, ambaya, like a murmuring
coals.
וליכליה, v'lichlei, and then you should eat it. Yeah, sounds tasty, of
all these things. Okay. רב חנינא אמר, Rav Chanina amar, מי רגלים
בני ארבעים יום. mei raglayim b'nei arba'im yom. If you have water
that is forty days old water, if you have urine that is
forty days old. Okay, so some say it means that it's of
an infant forty days, some say it's been stayed out forty days.
Anyway, what do you do? So this is good for a lot
of different things. בר זיני, bar zini, a little... a little cup
of this, drinking it I suppose, לזיבורא, l'zibura, is good for... for
wasp stings. רביעתא, reviata, a רביעית, revi'is, like I said, three and
a half ounces, לעקרבא, l'akrava, scorpion's stings. פלגא ריבעא, palga riv'a, a
half of a ריבעא, riv'a, which is two רביעית, revi'is, a half
of a לוג, log, לגלויא, l'giluya, for uncovered water. ריבעא, riv'a, a
full לוג, log, אפילו לכשפים מעלי. afilu l'chishafim ma'aly. Oh, that's so
powerful that it even works against witchcraft. אמר רב יוחנן, amar Rav
Yochanan, אניגרון. anigron. אניגרון anigron which is... yeah, we had that. That's
some type of a... it's something boiled with... what is it? רש"י
Rashi says right... סתם אניגרון מיא דסילקי ודתרדי, stam anigron maya d'silki
v'ditardi, like water with... of what of... of radishes of various types
of... some they basically or... or beets, anyway, some type of a
water cooked with various vegetables. ואבנגר, v'avangar, and אבנגר, avangar, וצריקה. v'tzirika.
I forget what these things are. What does English say for this?
אבנגר avangar they say, which some sort of herb they say, what
kind is it? וצריקה v'tzirika is balsam, they say.
Okay fine. All right, Rashi says ותירקתא v'Tirakti sorry. Okay right, I'm
sorry, Rashi said, right, okay fine. Okay, so these various things מעלו,
ma'alu, those are good, בין מגילויא, bein migiluya, whether from uncovering water,
בין לכשפים, bein l'kashapim, whether for witchcraft. האי מאן דבלע חויא, hai
man d'bala chivya, a person that swallowed an actual snake לוכליה
כשותא, luchlei kshuta, they should make him feed hops, I think is
what it is, במילחא b'milcha in salt, וליהטיה תלתא מילי. v'lihateih tlata
milei.
And then he has he should run three mil, okay, and that'll
I don't know, process the poison or get it out or something.
רב שימי בר אשי Rav Shimi bar Ashi חזייא לההוא גברא, chazaya
l'hahu gavra, Rav Shimi bar Ashi saw a certain person דבלע חויא,
d'bala chivya, he swallowed a snake. אידמי ליה כפרשא, idmi lei k'farasha,
he appeared to him, he dressed up or someone appeared to him
like a horseman אוכלייה כשותא במילחא, ochlei kshuta b'milcha, he made him
eat hops in salt, ורהטיה קמיה תלתא מילי, v'rahateih kameih tlata milei,
and he basically I don't know, chased after him on the horse
and made him run three mil, for you know, was good for
him, you know, for putting, you know, scare him, ונפק מיניה גובי
גובי, u'nafak mineih gubi gubi, and it came out from him like
lumps and lumps, this, you know, pieces and pieces, this snake. איכא
דאמרי, ika d'amri, some say רב שימי בר אשי Rav Shimi bar
Ashi בלע חויא, bala chivya, Rav Shimi bar Ashi wasn't the guy
with the remedy, he was the one that actually had swallowed the
snake. אתי אליהו, ati Eliyahu, Elijah came, אידמי ליה כפרשא, idmi lei
k'farasha, he made he looked like a horse rider, a horseman, אוכלייה
כשותא במילחא ורהטיה קמיה תלתא מילי, ochleih kshuta b'milcha v'rahateih kameih tlata
milei, made him eat hops and salt, and made him run in
front of him three mil, ונפק מיניה גובי גובי, u'nafak mineih gubi
gubi, it came out lumps, you know, clumps and clumps. האי מאן
דטרקיה חויא, hai man d'tarkei chivya, somebody that a snake has bit,
ליתי עוברא דחמרא, leiti uvra d'chamra, take the, take a fetus of
a donkey חיורתא, chivarta, of a white doggy, ולקרעיה, u'likreih, and, you
know, cut it up, cut it open, ולוסביה עילויה, v'losveih ilaveih, and
put it on the snake bite.
And הני מילי hani milei though you here you need to sit
on it.
Oh really? Sit on it. ולוסביה עילויה. v'losveih ilaveih. Okay, hmm, okay,
interesting.
What does, what does Steinzalts say? Sit on it or put it
on? Put it on. Put it on, right. Yeah, I think it's
put it on it. ולוסביה עילויה, v'losveih ilaveih, yeah, I guess it
could go either way. I'd have to have somebody who really knows
the grammar better than me. Okay.
What's the Rabbi doing eating a snake?
Accidental I guess. Or a worm kind? Yeah, maybe a, yeah, being
in spaghetti, who knows.
I have no idea.
הני מילי, hani milei, anyway, now onto snake bite, we're off of
eating the snake. והני מילי, v'hani milei, and this is only דלא
אישתכח טריפה, d'la ishtakach treifa, that's only if the mother wasn't a
treifa. ההוא בר קשא, hahu bar kasha, a certain officer of the
king, a Jewish officer of the king, דפומבדיתא, d'Pumbedita, of Pumbedita, דטרקיה
חויא, d'tarkei chivya, a snake bit him. הוו תליסר חמרי חיורתא בפומבדיתא,
havu tlaysar chamrei chivarta b'Pumbedita, there were thirteen white donkeys in Pumbedita,
you figure one of them you could get a fetus out of
it. קרעינהו לכולהו, kraineihu l'chuleihu, they opened them all up, ואישתכחו טריפן,
v'ishtakchu treifan, they were found, so I heard actually found that the
problem is that the fetus not be a treifa. Anyway, it's not
clear. Anyway, so they couldn't be used, because either the fetus or
the mother was a treifa and that was one of the criteria.
So what is he going to do? So הוי חדא בההוא גיסא
דפומבדיתא, havay chada b'hahu gisa d'Pumbedita, there was one donkey on the
other side of Pumbedita, white donkey, that maybe they could use the
fetus. אדאזלי מייתי לה אכלה אריה, ad'azlei maytei lah achlah aryeh, by
the time they went to get it, an animal, a lion had
eaten it. So this guy is really in trouble, any type of
remedy he's trying is, you know, some seems like from heaven they're
preventing him from the remedy. So there must be some other interpretation.
אמר להו אביי, amar lehu Abaye, so Abaye said to them, I
don't know, the people who were work, trying to help this guy,
דילמא חיויא דרבנן טרקיה, dilma chivya d'rabanan tarkei, maybe it wasn't just
stam a snake, it was the snake of the rabbis. What does
that mean? ולית ליה אסותא, v'leit lei asuta, it has no healing.
דכתיב ופורץ גדר ישכנו נחש, d'chtiv u'poretz geder yishchenu nachash, somebody who
breaks the through the gate, a snake should bite him, which is
used basically for a general sort of like rhetoric about not, you
know, violating sort of like rabbinic norms and standards, don't break break
through the gate, don't violate those standards. And if you do, a
snake'll come get you. So this person he must have, he must
be some, he must be defending the honor of the rabbis, he
violated something and that's why none of these remedies are working. Yes.
Don't they always think the ריש גלותא Reish Galuta and people like
that aren't so observant?
That is true. And this guy was right working for the government,
that could be. That's true. There are other Gemaras like this about
translating this pasuk ופורץ גדר ישכנו נחש poretz geder yishchenu nachash somewhat
literally. אמרו ליה אין רבי, amru lei in Rebbe, you know what
Rebbe, that's right, דכי נח נפשיה דרב, d'ki nach nafshia d'Rav,
because when Rav had died,
was dying, גזר רב יצחק בר ביסנא דליכא דלימטי אסא וגידמי לבי
הילולא. gazar Rav Yitzchak bar Bisna d'leika d'limti asa v'gidmei l'vei hilula.
So Rav Yitzchak bar Bisna said that made a, made an edict
that in like because of, you know, the mourning for Rav and
recognizing the loss, nobody should bring hadasim and gidmei, which is what's
gidmei again here? Hold on. What?
What does it say here?
Oh yeah, palm branches to a, you know, to a wedding feast,
you know, so a little giving something up because of the tragedy
of Rav having died, בטבלא b'tavla or with bells, some say davka
together with bells because sometimes that's in the girsa.
Okay. And he went, ואזל איהו, v'azal ihu, and he went, אמטי
וגדיל לביצו לבטבלה, amti v'gidil l'beitzu l'betavla, and he went and he
did it. So you see it wasn't even like a standard איסור
דרבנן, issur d'rabbanan, it was just a certain type of a rabbinic
like localized rabbinic edict, and nevertheless he violated, he was not respectful
of those norms of that גדר. geder. So טרכיה חיויא ומית, tarchia
chivyia umis, so therefore the snake bit him and he died. האי
מאן, hai man, yes, fits in with the other גמרות. Gemaras.
Exactly, exactly. At least it's not, this is not the גמרא Gemara
before about שמואל Shmuel not showing רב Rav where the bathroom was.
Okay, so this here with now here רב Rav was being, here
now רב Rav was being honored, was being protected. Okay. האי מאן
דכרכיה חיויא, hai man decharchei chivya, some person who a snake has
wrapped around him, or maybe is circling him, לנחות למיא, linhos l'maya,
go down into the water, ולסחופ דיקולא ארישיה, v'lischoof dikula areishia, and
put a דיקולא, dikula, put like a basket on your head,
ולהדקיה מיניה, ul'hadke minei, and then hopefully that as you're going down
into the water the snake is like getting off of you and
it'll go on top of the basket, okay, or into the basket.
So tilt the basket towards the snake. דכי סליק לביה, d'ki salik
l'vei, and when the snake goes into the basket, then לשדייה למיא,
lishdyei l'maya, throw the basket with the snake into the water, ולסלוק,
v'lislohk, and then וליתי v'lesei האי מאן דמיקני ביה hai man d'mikni
beih וליתי v'lesei and come, get out of the water and leave.
האי מאן דמיקני ביה חיויא, hai man d'mikni beih chivya, if somebody
a snake is like jealous of him, meaning I guess like threatening
to strike, or like focusing on you, רש"י Rashi says running after
him. So אי איכא חבריה בהדיה, ee ika chavrei bahadei, so if
you've got a friend with you,
so לירכביה ארבע גרמידי, lirkvei arba garmidei, so let the friend sort
of carry you for four אמות. amos. Exactly, yes, רש"י Rashi says
he can't, then the snake won't be able to smell you because
you're on the back of your, you're on the top of your
friend. Okay, so רש"י Rashi says the snake is on the ground,
he's smelling your footsteps. So if you get yourself picked up off
of the ground, then you're better, then you're okay. ואי לא, v'ilo,
and if that's not an option,
לישוור נגרא, lishavar nagra, so then what you should do is you
should jump over a stream of water, you know, like in all
those movies when they're tracking you and you go through water, here
it says jump over the water. But anyway, either the snake can't
pass over the water or he'll lose your scent. ואי לא ליעבר
נהרא, v'ilo l'avar nahara, and right, so if it doesn't work then
it's like a what do you call those, like a furrow of
water, then actually try to pass through a river.
ובליליא, uv'leilya, and at night, or maybe I don't know this isn't
an option, לוקמה לפורייה אארבע חביתא, lo k'fei l'puraiya a'arba chavisa, or
maybe you're home now in bed and you're afraid it's going to
come to get you when you sleep. So put your bed on
four barrels, so again your bed is raised off of the ground
and it won't be able to smell you. וניגני בי כוכבי, v'nignei
bei kochvei, and you should sleep in a sort of under the
stars, okay, so רש"י Rashi says it shouldn't come through the roof.
וליתי ארבע שונרי, v'leisei arba shunrei, take four cats, וליסרנהו בארבע כרעי
דפורייה, v'lisrinhu b'arba karei d'puraiya, and tie them to the four posts
of the bed, וליתי שחפי, v'leisei shachfi, and take like woodchips, ולישדייה
התם, v'lishdyei hasam, and put them all around your bed, so דכי
שמעי קליה, d'ki sham'e koli, because then the cats will hear as
the snake tries to slither through the woodchips and it'll make sound,
ואכלו ליה, v'achlu lei, and then they'll go and eat the snake.
Okay, so there you have it. I don't know, do cats eat
snake? I know mongoose eat, a mongoose will eat a snake. Cats
will eat a snake? I've heard it, so I don't know if
they eat them,
but they'll catch them, kill them. Great, okay. האי מאן
דרהיט בתריה, hai man d'raiteih basrei, now that's when it was presumably
I don't know smelling you, now it's actively running after you.
לירהוט בי חלא, lirhat bei chalsa, then you should run between sand,
that somehow the snake won't be able to follow you so well
between sand. I don't know what that's about. Okay, האי איתתא, hai
iteta, a woman, דחזיא חיויא, d'chazya chivya, that saw a snake, ולא
ידעה אי יהב דעתיה עילויה, v'lo yada ee yeihav deitei iloiyah, and
she doesn't know if the snake has her, has, if thinking about
her. Meaning this is going back to that, you know, to the
whole מדרשים Midrashim that basically the snake desired to sleep with חוה,
Chavah, and that's why she was trying to kill אדם, Adam, you
know, there's obviously very like, you know, seems to like be though
very phallic type of imagery going here. So the snake is sexually
interested in this woman, that seems to be the case. Okay,
I'm not sure if, lo, אי יהב דעתיה עילויה, ee yeihav deitei
iloiyah, if not. So תשלוך מנייהו, tishlach manei, very interesting here, take
her clothes off, all her clothes, whatever, ותשתדי קמיה, v'nishtadei kamei,
and throw it in front of the snake. אי מיכרך בהו, ee
michrich b'hu, if the snake starts like wrapping itself within the clothes,
דעתיה עילויה, deitei iloiyah, then you know the snake is actually interested
in the woman, smelling her clothes, whatever, really like seeing this as
like a sexual type of a thing. ואי לא, v'ilo,
and if not, then לא יהב דעתיה עילויה, lo yeihav deitei iloiyah,
then it's not thinking about her. Okay. מאי תקנתה, mai takanta, now
let's say it is thinking about her, what should she do? תשמש
קמיה tishamesh kamey so have sex in front of him with her
husband. I guess know that he’s a spoken for woman or something.
It’s very, again, the sexual thing theme here is very seems to
be very present. איכא דאמרי ika d’amri some say no, כל שכן
kol shekein דאתי ליצבויי d’atyei l’itzvi then you’re just enticing
his sexual desire.
אלא ela yes, it’s like I know. Okay, אלא ela right, yes
the מדרש midrash is that the snake saw אדם וחוה Adam v’Chava
having I don’t know. אלא ela תשקול ממזיא ומטופרא tishkol mimazya u’mitufra
take from her hair and from her nails ותשדי ביה v’tishdei beih
and throw it at him ותימא v’teima and say to him דישטנא
אנא dishtana ana I am a נידה niddah I am a menstruant.
Now this, if it wasn’t already disturbing about the snake sort of
sexually interested in the woman, this seems to be touching into the
whole sense of the taboo of נידה niddah not just the הלכה
halacha of נידה niddah that the things associated with a woman of
נידה niddah are like
injurious and has like these this evil around it and so basically
so she well exactly I don’t know how the snake knows the
language she’s speaking but somehow this will snake oh well she’s a
נידה niddah that’s it I’m out of here. So okay but again
but it does seem to be like this like negative demonic power
or some type of stuff going on within the hair and the
fingernails of this woman. האי איתתא דעייל בה חיויא hai ittata d’ayeil
bah chivya now if a woman the snake actually entered into her,
okay, which means what you think it means,
ליפסע lifsa let her let her
walk וליסווא אטרתי חביצי v’lisva atartei chavizai and sit on on two
barrels I’m
sorry ליפסע lifsa
to actually part
her leg yes I’m sorry to part her leg right right thank
you I misunderstood that part her leg over two barrels so spread
her legs basically ליתי בישרא שמנא leiti bisra shamna and bring fatty
meat ולשדי אגומרי v’lishdei agumrei and put it by the have it
burn on coals וליתי אגנא דתחלי v’leiti agana d’tachlei and take a
barrel of תחלי tachlei which was
cress וחמרא ריחנא v’chamra reichana
and very aromatic wine ולותי התם v’lavtei hatam
and put it there all under her legs right because we’re trying
to basically get the snake to come out right.
Okay
what about the running three miles
the snake already entered into her ולחרקינהו בהדי הדדי ulcharquinehu bahadi hadadei
and basically sort
of mix them all up together ולנקוט צבתא בידה v’lincot tzavta biyadei
and she should take a like a tongs in her hand דהכי
מרח ריחא dehachi marach reicha because when the snake smells this נפיק
ואתי nafik v’atei it’ll come out of her and then she’ll be
able to grab it with the tongs ולנקטיה v’linkteia and she can
grab it וליקלייה בנורא v’likleyeia benura and burn it into the fire
because she’s got some coals going on there. Okay דאי לאו הכי
de’i lav hachi and if she doesn’t do this הדר עייל בה
hadar ayeil bah it’ll go right back into her.
So I guess that’s the thing with the running thing while
it versus if it enters into her what if it attaches itself
to his member yes that
they weren’t concerned about that it really has to do with the
very I think the phallic imagery of the snake and the story
of the גן עדן Gan Eden I think that’s what it was
about. Okay כל האוכלין kol ha’ochlin now moving on into the משנה
mishna but the good point is look we’re catching up. כל האוכלין
kol ha’ochlin okay all foods you can eat except even if you’re
doing it for health purposes. By the way there’s an interesting question
about vitamins are vitamins considered to be a food or are vitamins
considered to be a רפואה refuah you know because they’re like a
dietary supplement. So as I said in general nowadays most פוסקים poskim
try to interpret these prohibitions as narrowly as possible because it affects
your enjoyment of שבת Shabbos and your general health and the concerns
of it about שחיקת סממנים shchikat samamanim of grinding your medicine is
much doesn’t exist nowadays so they try to interpret these as generally
there’s a general move to interpret the to define the scope as
narrowly as possible. So vitamins is an interesting question a lot say
vitamins do not fall fall under אוכל ochel and not רפואה. refuah.
Really which means they need a הכשר. hechsher.
Well that’s the yeah that’s a related question that’s a very that’s
an excellent point right the הכשר hechsher issue about and they do
generally we say need a הכשר hechsher vitamins as opposed to other
things. Okay so כל האוכלין לאתויי מאי kol ha’ochlin l’atuyei mai what
is that coming to include לאתויי טחול לשיניים l’atuyei tchol l’shinayim if
you’re going to eat spleen for the liver
right
I’m sorry what I say liver cause spleen okay I’m sorry טחול
tchol right spleen for your teeth the spleen of some animal for
your teeth וכרשינין לבני מעיים v’karshinin livnei me’ayim כרשינין karshinin which is
I don’t know some other type of thing what is it כרשינין
karshinin vetch vetch there you go I can’t believe I didn’t remember
that okay leeks leeks or vetch for your stomach yeah I was
quoting stomach from the next thing okay that’s the so those foods
even though normal people who eats liver who eats or who eats.
Who eats spleen? Who eats vetch? I certainly never eat vetch anyway,
anyway. So because at least it's a I have no idea.
Anyway, so because at least it's a food that normal people will
eat under some circumstances, even if it's unusual, you can eat it
for your for your
for what's bothering you. כל המשקין עשויין לרפואה. Kol hamashkin asuyin lirfu'ah.
I all liquids to include what? לאתויי מי צלפין בחומץ Le-atuyei mei
tzalpin be-chometz to include this מי צלפין mei tzalpin in vinegar. What's
מי צלפין? mei tzalpin? רש"י Rashi says a fruit of צלף, tzalaf,
some type of a fruit. What is a צלף? tzalaf? Caper. Okay,
caper in vinegar. אמר ליה רבינא לרבא. Amar lei Ravina le-Rava. רבינא
Ravina said to רבא, Rava, מהו לשתות מי רגלים בשבת? Mahu lishtos
mei raglayim be-Shabbos? How about urine? Remember we said before that urine
was such an effective remedy. So now of course who would normally
drink urine? So אמר ליה, amar lei, תנינא כל המשקין שותה. tanina
kol hamashkin shosseh. It says you can drink liquids. ומי רגלים לא
שתו אינשי. U-mei raglayim lo shassu inshi. And people don't drink urine.
Now what is, how is he proving it from the משנה? Mishna?
Presumably saying it's not called משקה. mashkeh. משקה Mashkeh doesn't just mean
that it has a liquid form, it means something that's considered to
be a potable liquid. I have no idea. Maybe he wanted to
read the משנה Mishna
very formalistically. It's a drink, it's a משקה, mashkeh, you can literally
drink it. But of course how could you say this since the
משנה Mishna beforehand said, was speaking about that you can't drink מי
דקלים? mei dekalim? Why would he think urine would be different than
מי דקלים? mei dekalim? I have no idea.
In parts of India people do drink urine.
Okay, do they drink or
just... Okay. חוץ ממי דקלים. Chutz mi-mei dekalim. So מי דקלים mei
dekalim is the one thing you can't, that's obviously done for remedy,
assuming that's also your intent. Again, your intent matters. If your intent
is not for remedy, it's okay.
תנא חוץ ממי דקרים. Tana chutz mi-mei dekarim. Another version of this
is water of piercing. So מאי תנא מי דקרים? mah tana mei
dekarim? So what's the meaning of that piercing? שכן דוקין את המרה.
She-hen dokin es hamarah. They pierce through the gallbladder. Okay, so maybe
that's why it was drunk for some type of a gallbladder problem.
ומאן דאמר מי דקלים, U-man de-amar mei dekalim, a palm tree, שיותין
מבין שני דקלי. she-yotzin mi-bein shenei dikla. That it comes between some
water that emerges out of between two palm trees basically. מאי מי
דקלים? Mah mei dekalim? So what does that mean? אמר רבה בר
בר חנה, Amar Rabbah bar Bar Bruna, תרתי צלאי איכא במערבא. tarti
tzalai ika be-ma'arava. There are two palm trees in ארץ ישראל. Eretz
Yisrael.
ונפקא עינא דמיא בינייהו. Ve-nafkka aina de-maya beinei-hu. So it's not any
two palm trees, two particular ones, and a spring of water comes
between them. כסא קמא ממרפי. Kasa kama mimarpei. If you take the
first cup from this
spring, it'll
like it'll like heal you or also means like loosen, you know,
your if you have what's it called, if you're constipation, if you're
constipation it'll loosen it and help you and help you relieve
yourself. אידך משלשל. Idach meshalshel. Then it'll cause you to actually have
diarrhea. ואידך כי היכי דעייל הכא נפיק נפיק. Ve-idach ki heichei de-ayeil
hacha nafik nafik. Anything that goes in up top will come out
on the bottom. It'll go straight through you, okay, if any more
food that you eat. So anyway basically this was some form of
a diuretic. אמר עולא, Amar Ulla, לדידי שתי שכר דבבלאי, le-di shasyei
shichra de-Bavlai, ומעלי מיני ממי הני מיא. u-ma'ali minei mei-hanei maya.
I actually drank the Babylonian
mead and it was better even than this water. That was really
good as a diuretic. והוא דלא רגיל ביה ארבעים יומין. Ve-hu de-lo
ragil bei arba'im yomin. That's only if you haven't drunk it for
the last 40 days, then it'll have that effect.
Okay, I guess they didn't have coffee, right? Coffee is a pretty
good diuretic. רב יוסף אמר Rav Yosef amar what?
Only in the Middle Ages did coffee become...
Yeah, I know. There's a whole article about how the whole practice
of staying up on שבועות Shavuos night only began after coffee was
introduced into Europe. Okay, also not only that, also the practice of
of תיקון חצות Tikkun Chatzos of staying up of getting up at
midnight to pray for the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. Anyway. Okay. רב
יוסף אמר Rav Yosef amar what? זיתום המצרי. zeysum hamitzri.
This Egyptian זיתום. zeysum. Here's how you make it.
תילתא שערי. Tilsa sa'arei. It's a third of barley.
ותילתא כורתמי. Ve-silsa kortemi. A third of
saffron. ותילתא מילחא. Ve-silsa milcha. A third salt. Okay, well we'll find
out in a minute what you do with it. רב פפא אמר
Rav Papa amar תילתא חיטי. tilsa chitti. No, not barley but actually
wheat, presumably wheat flour or
something. ותילתא כורתמי ותילתא מילחא. Ve-silsa kortemi ve-silsa milcha. וסימנך, Ve-simanach, just
so you remember whether it is barley or wheat, סיסני. Sisani. That
the word
סיסני Sisani which is a certain type of a vessel, so it
has a ס ס. samech samech. So רב יוסף Rav Yosef says
שערי. sa'arei. So ס ס, samech samech, it's רב יוסף Rav Yosef
that says barley, because it's important to remember who says which. ושתי
להו בין דבחא לעצרתא. Ve-shatyei lehu bein divcha le-atzarta. And if you
drink this between פסח Pesach and
שבועות. Shavuos. דבחא Divcha like זבח פסח zevach Pesach and עצרתא atzerta
is שבועות, Shavuos, which is the Rabbinic term for שבועות. Shavuos. דקמי
מרפי. Di-kami marpei. Anybody that has
constipation it'll loosen the bowels, מרפי ליה. marpei lei. ודרפי קמי ליה.
U-derapei kami lei. And somebody that has too loose bowels it'll help
it'll help do the opposite. What's that called, the
opposite of a diuretic? An antispasmodic or an anti-diarrheal, diarrhea I guess.
Okay anyway, this is when you can't
drink it between פסח Pesach and שבועות? Shavuos? No, this is if
you drink it at this time of the year, presumably it's effective
in the springtime, that's the idea.
You can't drink it any other time?
Maybe it won't be as effective, I don't know. Okay, בכוס עקרין.
becos ikrin. Yes,
okay, because of saffron. Saffron, yeah, right.
Saffron was once worth its weight in gold?
Really? Wow. Oh my god. Okay. All right, בכוס עקרין becos ikrin
and a cup of roots, you know, that has roots sort of,
you know, that
were immersed in the liquid and somehow so that liquid now with
the root juices, that's obviously for medicinal purposes. מאי כוס עקרין? Mai
cos ikrin? What does this mean? Like what type of roots, how
would you do it? אמר רבי יוחנן ליתי מתקל זוזא קומא. Amar
Rabbi Yochanan leisi miskal zuza quma. You take the weight of a
זוז zuz
of קומא. quma.
What is the S?
No, קומא אלכסנדריא. quma Alexandriya.
I'm sorry, קומא אלכסנדריא, quma Alexandriya, Alexandrian קומא, quma, which רש״י Rashi
says is some type of a sap from trees. ומתקל זוזא גביא
גילא U-miskal zuza gavya gila and the weight of a זוז zuz
of, רש״י Rashi says it's
alum, alum. ומתקל זוזא כורכמא רישקא, U-miskal zuza korkema rishka, which רש״י
Rashi says is, כורכמא korkema is saffron, is also I think saffron.
That's a huge amount of saffron.
But it's only a זוז zuz weight. I know, a זוז, zuz,
a זוז zuz is not so much, a זוז zuz is a
weight of a whatever, but anyway, only a few grams. Maybe. Anyway,
but it's funny because רש״י Rashi says it means garden saffron. But
I used a different term before for saffron, but כורכמא korkema is
I think the more common one for saffron. How did they translate
כורכמא? korkema?
He says yeah, he says garden saffron.
Garden saffron, yeah, but before it was a different term, but כורכמא,
korkema, I know, כורכמא korkema is I think the משנה Mishnayic term
for saffron. Anyway, ושחקינהו בהדי הדדי, u-shchininhu bahadi hadadi, grind it all
together. לזבה, Le-zava, now here's what it's good for. If a woman
is a זבה, zava, if she actually is bleeding during not during
her period, so
תלתא בחמרא. telasa be-chamra. So לזבה תלתא, le-zava telasa,
one minute, oh, take all three of these ingredients and drink it
with wine. ולא מעקרא Ve-lo me'akra and it won't cause any it
won't sterilize her, it won't cause any side effects.
לירקונא, Le-yerkona, if you've got jaundice, תרין, trein, take only two of
the ingredients, doesn't say which תרין, trein, בשיכרא be-shichra in and take
it together with mead or beer. ומעקר U-me'aker but there is a
little bit of a problem which is that it'll cause you to
become sterile. לזבה, Le-zava, now the גמרא Gemara analyzes this. לזבה תלתא
בחמרא ולא מעקרא. Le-zava telasa be-chamra ve-lo me'akra. Okay, now we're going
to add to this statement. ואי לא, Ve-ilo, if that wasn't effective
for this woman who's a זבה, zava, ליתי תלתא קפיזי, leisi telasa
kafizi, take three like little vessels of work,
רש״י Rashi says it's not so little, it's a vessel that holds
three לוגין, loughs, so it's about a לוג log is about twelve
ounces, so that's big, okay, it's like whatever thirty-six ounces of
סומקי פרסאי, simchi parsai, Persian onion, ונשלוק בחמרא, ve-nishlok be-chamra, and boil
it in wine, ונשקייה, ve-nishkaye, and drink it. ונימא לה, Ve-neima lah,
and say to her the woman, קומי מזובייך, kumi mi-zovayich, get up
from your flow. So somehow it's like the woman who said to
the snake, you know, somehow if you say things while you're drinking
the remedy, that helps in the effective. ואי לא, Ve-ilo, and if
that wasn't effective, לאותבה אפרשת דרכים, losva a-parshas drachim, have the woman
sit by a crossroads, ולנקוטא כסא דחמרא בידה, ve-linkota kassa de-chamra bideih,
and she should take a cup of wine in her hand, וליתי
איניש מאחורה, ve-leisi inish me-achorah, and a person should come from behind
her, וליבעתה, ve-livsah, scare her. So it's like a cure for like
the hiccups or something.
Why sitting at a crossroads though?
I mean I don't know, what do I know? ונימא לה, Ve-leima
lah, and say to her, קומי מזובייך, kumi mi-zovayich, get up from
your flow. ואי לא, Ve-ilo, and if that's not effective, ליתי בונא
דכמונא, leisi buna de-kamona, take a בונא, buna, רש״י Rashi says it's
like a handful of כמונא, kamona,
cumin, thank
you, ובונא דמוריקא, u-buna de-morika, and a handful where we're back to
the saffron,
ובונא דשבליסא, u-buna de-shavlisa, and a handful
of fenugreek I think, is that what it says, fenugreek? Okay,
ונשלוק בחמרא, ve-nishlok be-chamra, and boil it in wine, ונשקייה, ve-nishkaye, and
drink it, ונימא לה, ve-neima lah, and say to her קומי מזובייך,
kumi mi-zovayich, get up from your flow. ואי לא, Ve-ilo, if that
wasn't effective, ליתי שיתין שיעי דדנא, leisi shishin shi'ei de-dana, take sixty
seals of a barrel, often sixty is an exaggeration, ולשוויי, ve-lishvei, and
and like you know immerse it in water,
ונימא לה, ve-leima lah, and say to her קומי מזובייך kumi mi-zovayich
and get up from your flow. Actually, ולשוויי lishvei is put them
on her. You what?
ולשוויי Lishvei is put them on her.
Oh,
I thought put them in water, how'd that help her? Yeah I
don't know. רש״י Rashi says בכשישא דשרו במיא, be-chashisha de-shoro be-maya, I'm
not clear, anyway, okay, maybe. ואי לא, Ve-ilo, if that didn't work,
ליתי פשטינא, leisi pashtina, take a certain type of a grass called
פשטינא. pashtina. and rub it on her and say to her קומי
זובייך. Kumi zoveich. ואי לא, Ve'ee lo, if that doesn't work, ליתי
חרנוגא, leisei charnoga, Rashi says it's a type of a grass that
grows between the what do you call it thorn
bushes דהיכסא dehikhsa of a thorn bush, רומיזא romisa of a Roman
thorn bush, excuse me,
וליקלה velliklah and burn it,
וליספא בשחקי דקיתנא velispah beshchakei dekitnah and take
these ashes with worn-out linen
garments בקיטא bekayeta in the summer, okay so you've got to hope
that it's summer,
ובשחקי דעמר גופנא בסיתוא u'veshchakei de'amar gufna besitva or if it's the
winter, then take it with
worn-out cotton garments and I don't know what you're supposed to do
with that. Somehow she maybe holds on to it, I don't know
what she does with it after you take it in these garments,
maybe she rubs the garments on her or something, right. Okay. ואי
לא, Ve'ee lo, if that didn't work,
ליכרי שבע בירי, lichrei sheva beirei, dig seven holes,
וליקלי בהו שבישתא ילדתא דערלה velliklei behu shevishta yaldata de'orlah and burn
in them seven young shoots
of a grapevines of orlah first within their first three years,
ולינקוט כסא דחמרא בידה, velinkut kasa dechamra beyadah, take a cup of
wine in her hand, ולווקמה מהא ולוותבה מהא, vellikmah meha velovtebah meha,
get up from one of the holes and sit in the next
hole, ולווקמה מהא ולוותבה מהא, vellikmah meha velovtebah meha, get up from
one, sit in the next, אכל חדא וחדא achal chada vechada on
every hole, לימא לה leima lah say to her קומי זובייך, Kumi
zoveich, get up from your flow. ואי לא, Ve'ee lo, and if
that didn't work, you wonder like why they had so many remedies
for this flow, like was this a big problem? I mean how
often would a woman bleed during their not their menstrual period? Maybe
it was flows that wasn't bleeding flows, maybe it was other types
of flows. Anyway, you know, ואי לא, Ve'ee lo, if that didn't
work, ליתי סמידא, leisei samida, take
a
solet, a
flour, וליסכא
מפלגא ולתחתא velischah mipalga u'letata should sort of like put it on
her from her waist down, ולימא לה veleima lah say to her
קומי זובייך. Kumi zoveich. ואי לא, Ve'ee lo, and if that didn't
work, this
seems like the easiest thing
to do, just put some
flour on yourself, okay. ואי לא, Ve'ee lo, ליתי ביעתא דנעמיתא, leisei
beita dena'amita, take an egg of an ostrich, וליקלה velliklah and burn
it, וליספא בשחקי דקיתנא בקיטא velispah beshchakei dekitnah bekayeta and take it
in worn-out linen garments in the summer, ובשחקי דעמר גופנא בסיתוא u'veshchakei
de'amar gufna besitva and worn-out cotton garments in the winter. ואי לא,
Ve'ee lo, and if that didn't work, ליפתח לה חביתא דחמרא, lifthach
lah chavita dechamra, open up for her barrels of wine, there's a
wine is a very big thing here, one has to assume that
all this wine stuff is because wine is a red type of
a liquid, so that there's some sense there of this sense that
the wine is, I don't know, drawing it out from her, but
there's some type of a sympathetic medicine going on here, that's my
guess, anyway, okay, לשמה lishmah and when you open the barrels of
wine you should say I'm opening it for this woman and then
somehow maybe the barrel will be open with the wine rather than
the woman open with her flow, that's what my sense is what's
going on here. ואי לא, Ve'ee lo, and if that doesn't work,
ליתי שערתא דמשתכחא בכפשותא דכודנא חיוורא, leisei se'arta demishtakecha bekaphshuta dechudna chivra,
take a what is this again, oh take a barley
bean which is found in the excrement of white donkeys,
אי נקטה חד יומא ee naktah chad yoma
if she holds on to this barley bean for one day, פסקה,
paskah, then it'll cause her bleeding to stop, תרי יומי Trei yomei
for two days,
פסקה תרי יומי paskah trei yomei I'm sorry it'll stop for two
days, ואי נקטה תלתא יומי Ve'ee naktah tlata yomei if she holds
on for three days, פסקה לעולם paskah le'olam she'll never have to
deal with this flow again. Okay. Phew! All right, I don't know
if it means she'll never bleed again or she won't have this
unusual flow. Moving on.
לירקונא, Leierkona, now all of that was what you would do if
you would use all of these three ingredients in this cos ikrin
for a flow and here's what if it wasn't effective. Now we
go back to if you use two of the ingredients, it's effective
for jaundice. לירקונא תרין בשכרא, Leierkona trein beshachra, you take two of
these ingredients in beer, ומעקר, ume'aker, but it has a little side
effect, it makes you sterile. ואי לא, Ve'ee lo, and if that
wasn't effective, ליתי רישא דשיבוטא במלחא, leisei reisha deshibuta bemilcha, take the
head of a shibuta fish in salt, ולישלוק בשכרא velishlok beshachra and
basically boil it in beer, ולישתי velishti and drink the resultant liquid.
ואי לא, Ve'ee lo, if that wasn't effective, ליתי מוניני דקמצי, leisei
munini dekamtei, take
what
is this
again, locusts, oh right, okay, Rashi says right, some type of right,
some type of a brine or juice of grasshoppers. ואי ליכא מוניני
דקמצי, ve-ei leika monini dekamtsi, if you don't have that available, ליתי
מוניני דנקירי, leisai monini denikiri, then take the type of a of
a brine or whatever, some type of the juice from certain, from
small little birds. וליעיל
לבי בני ve-ye'ol le-bei banei and go into, take it into a
bathhouse where you got all the steam going. ולישפייה ve-lishfyei and then
you should put it on, rub it on you. ואי ליכא בי
בני, ve-ei leika bei banei, if there's not a bathhouse, לוקמה בין
תנורא לכותלא, lokmeih bein tanura le-kotala, the person should stand between an
oven and a wall; basically it's the use of the steam and
heat for this jaundice. What by the way is the way to
cure jaundice?
It depends what's causing it. I mean, it can be from an
inflammation like from a viral infection. In sun, babies they put in
the sun.
So the sweating and heat, is that effective at all?
No. Sunlight. It depends what causes it.
ואמר רבי יוחנן, ve-amar Rabbi Yochanan, הרוצה שיחממנו, ha-rotzeh she-yechamemenu, if you
want to warm the guy up, does jaundice cause shivers or something?
It depends what causes the jaundice.
Fine. Anyway, okay, so you should wrap him up well in your
like in your cloak, which seems like a pretty obvious advice, you
want to keep somebody warm, you wrap him up well in your
blanket.
Rashi says it might mean, you know, use the garment of somebody
else who has this illness. Anyway, רב אחא בר יוסף חש ביה,
Rav Acha bar Yosef chash beih, Rav Acha, he had this problem
with jaundice. עבד ליה רב כהנא, avad leih Rav Kahana, so Rav
Kahana did for him, you know, this wrapping up of the cloak.
So presumably it doesn't just keep him warm. ואתסי, ve-itsi, and he
actually got cured. ואי לא, ve-ei lo, if that wasn't effective, ליתי
תלתא כפיזי דתמרי, leisai tlata kafizei de-tamri, take three, you know, of
these sort of vessels filled with dates, פרסייתא, parsiata, Persian dates, ותלתא
כפיזי דקירא דנשתרופי, ve-tlata kafizei de-kira de-nishtarufi, and three vessels of דקירא
דנשתרופי, de-kira de-nishtarufi, which is Rashi says it's wax that sort of
floats on the top of a type of a beehive, I guess,
of honey,
ותלתא כפיזי אהלא, ve-tlata kafizei ahala, and three and three of vessels
filled with אהלא, ahala, which is which is aloe is what Steinzaltz
says, תולנא, tolana, red red, red aloe. ולשלקינהו בשיכרא ve-lishalkinehu be-shichra and
boil it up in beer, ולישתי ve-lishtei and drink it. ואי לא,
ve-ei lo, if that didn't work, ליתי עילא בר חמרתא, leisai eila
bar chamarta, then you should take a foal of donkeys, a donkey
foal. וליגלח מציעתא דרישיה, ve-liglach metziata de-reisheih, and you should shave the
middle of the head. ולישדי ליה דמא מאפוסיה, ve-lishdei leih dama me-afuseih,
and you should take blood that comes out of the forehead of
this of this foal, וליסדי ארישיה, ve-lisdei a-reisheih, put it on the
head of the guy that has jaundice. וליזהר מעיניה, ve-lizahar me-eineih, and
he should be very careful it doesn't get into his eyes דלא
ליסמינהו, de-la lisamyinehu, so it shouldn't blind him. ואי לא, ve-ei lo,
if that didn't work, ליתי רישא דברחא, leisai reisha de-barcha, you should
take the head of a ram דמנח בקיבצא de-manach be-kivtsa that was
in an, oh sorry, Rashi says that it was put in vinegar,
right, that was sort of כבוש, kavush, right, ולישלוק בשיכרא ve-lishlok be-shichra
and boil it in a beer, ולישתי ve-lishtei and drink it. ואי
לא, ve-ei lo, if that didn't work, ליתי דבר אחר חוטרנא, leisai
davar acher chutrana, then you should take a striped, like a pig,
that's why it's called
דבר אחר, davar acher,
right, we don't like to say pigs, there's taboo around pigs. ולקורעיה,
ve-likreih, and tear it open וליסדי אליביה, ve-lisdei a-libeih, and put it
on his heart. Right, all this is for jaundice. ואי לא, ve-ei
lo, if that didn't work, ליתי כרתי מכבסותא דמישרא, leisai karti me-kabsusa
de-meishra, take a cress from leeks, I'm
sorry, מכבסותא me-kabsusa from the middle of the row in the garden
of the, you know, of the, of the where they're
growing. ההוא טייעא דחש ביה, hahu taya de-chash beih, there was a
certain nomad, a certain, you know, Arab that was that had this
illness. אמר להו לגינאי, amar lehu le-ginai, he said to the people
in the garden, שקולו גלימאי והבו לי מישרא דכרתי. shakulu glimai ve-havu
li meishra de-karti. He said, you know what? I'll swap you my
cloak for for this row of cress because he knew that that
was the remedy for it. יהבו ליה ואכל, yehavu leih ve-achal, so
they gave it to him and he
ate. אמר להו, amar lehu, so then he, so that was a
fair trade for everybody. So then he said אושלן גלימאי ואיגני ביה.
oshlan glimai ve-igni beih. He said, you know what? I know it's
your cloak now, but can I borrow it so at least I
can, you know, use it to sleep on? So call a little
bit, I need to take a little nap. איכריך וגנא ביה, ichrich
u-gna beih,
he wrapped it up, he slept on it. כד חמים, kad chamim,
then because the remedy was effective, it caused him to sort of
heat up because the whole, a lot of these things are all
about getting him hot and sweating, right? If you notice a lot
of the wrapping and the bathhouse or whatever. So his nap, he
heated up וקם נפל. ve-kam nafal. פורצא פורצא מינה purtza purtza minei
and then, you know, and then little bits of the cloak sort
of all sort of like, you know, all fell away because somehow,
I don't know, his heat and his fever, whatever, ruined the cloak.
So he basically managed to get the remedy and for free because
then he borrowed the cloak. I don't know why he didn't say
השואל חייב באונסין hashoel chayav b'onsin and he had to pay them
for it anyway. Alright, let's just read a little bit more context.
Now we actually turn to a halakhic discussion. So you see that?
I mean we did a daf and a half today. It's totally...
anyway, the הירוקתא ha'yerokta תרי trei ושיכרא דבי אקבי. v'shichra d'vei akvi.
It said, if you have jaundice, you use two of these ingredients
in beer and you will become sterile. ומי שרי? umi sharei? How
can you take something that's gonna make you sterile even if you're
willing to deal with the side effects? והתניא, vehatanya, and we turn
to the baraita, מניין לסירוס באדם שהוא אסור? minayin l'sirus b'adam shehu
asur? How do you know that you're not allowed to sterilize a
person? תלמוד לומר ובארצכם לא תעשו. Talmud lomar uv'artzchem lo ta'asu. It
speaks about not bringing animals that are, you know, that are sterilized
and says you should not do this in your land. So you
do it, right? ובכם לא תעשו. uvachem lo ta'asu. You can't even
do it in you, amongst you you can't sterilize a person. דברי
רבי חנינא. divrei Rabbi Chanina. That's what Rabbi Chanina says. He says,
no, הני מילי היכא דקמיכוין. hani milei heicha d'kamichaven. That's when you're
doing something for the intentional purpose, intended purpose of sterilizing. הכא מאליו
הוא. hacha me'elav hu. Here it's a side effect. You're basically trying
to heal the guy and this is a side effect. דאמר רבי
יוחנן, d'amar Rabbi Yochanan, הרוצה שיסרס תרנגול, harotze sheyisares tarnagol, if you
want to sterilize a rooster, יטול כרבלתו, yitol karbalto, you can take
its, its, what is it, what's it called, the crown, what, the
comb, ומסתרס מאליו, umis'tares me'elav, and then it will naturally be. So
that seems, that seems that's not just a question that it wasn't
your intent, that also seems that you were not doing something which
is considered a direct act of sterilization. You weren't actually acting on
the genitals. You were doing something else. You're just removing the comb.
But it says you can't neuter an animal, like if I wanted
to neuter... Right.
So that's a real issue.
If you did this to a תרנגול, tarnagol, you couldn't neuter it,
you'd have to do something
else.
Well, so that is actually a question about how you neuter animals
and some about having a, having a non-Jew do it or causing...
I'll,
if you want, I'll, I can bring in, there's some תשובות tshuvot
about that. I'll, if I've got a chance, I'll bring in tomorrow.
Anyway, so presumably this was an evidence that you could do it
indirectly, but it's pretty interesting what's considered here indirect because in the
second case you were intending to do it but you weren't acting
directly maybe on the genitals. But that's, you know, does that mean
I can intentionally drink something that makes me sterile as long as
I'm not doing something directly on that part of the body? Anyway,
so the Gemara says, but that's the, at least we'll talk about
it more tomorrow, let's just end with this. So the Gemara says
והאמר רב אסי, v'ha'amar Rav Assi, one minute, that's not a proof.
That is not real sterilizing the rooster. Rav Assi says רמות רוחא
הוא דנקיט ליה. ramus rucha hu denakit lei. It's just he's very
proud of its, of its comb and when you remove it it
really like hurts its self-image or something and that's why it's sterile
but it's not actually biologically sterilizing it so that's not relevant for
our discussion. They won't have sex because it feels...
Right, exactly.
אלא ela says the Gemara בסירי.
bisari. You're only allowed,
you're only allowed to do this remedy for somebody who already is
sterile. Okay. So it's already made sterile? Good question. So it's telling
you it makes you sterile so you should know not to do
it unless you're already sterile. Anyway we will continue with this tomorrow
with this question about parameters of sterilization which are actually quite relevant.
Okay.